Guide to the Stan Weir Papers TAM.279
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Stan Weir Papers
1935-1990
1962-1974
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Weir, Stan
TAM.279
13.25 Linear Feet in 13 record cartons and 1 index card box
This collection contains a limited selection of the personal and professional papers of longshoreman and labor educator Stan Weir. Stan Weir (1921-2001) was an educator and labor activist from California. Born in Los Angeles in 1921, Weir had a long career in across a variety of industries, working as a seaman, autoworker, house painter, Teamster, grocery clerk, publisher, and university professor. This collection primarily documents Weir’s involvement in the seventeen-year-long legal case Williams v. Pacific Maritime Association-International Longshore and Warehouse Union, which contested the firing of eighty-two B-class longshoremen in the summer of 1963 in San Francisco. This collection also contains administrative and editorial files from Weir’s publishing company Singlejack Books, which he started with Robert Miles in 1977, and a small amount of correspondence between Weir’s mother Florence Hoggard Weir and his stepfather Albert Nicholas, who was one of founders of New Orleans jazz.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Scope and Content Note
The Stan Weir Papers (dated 1935-1990) contain a limited selection of the personal and professional papers of longshoreman and labor educator Stan Weir. Materials contained in this collection document various moments in Weir’s personal life and career, but they are not comprehensive. These papers primarily document Weir’s involvement in the seventeen-year-long legal case Williams v. Pacific Maritime Association-International Longshore and Warehouse Union, which contested the firing of eighty-two B-class longshoremen in the summer of 1963. These files make up the majority of the collection and contain records documenting the case proceedings, including court briefs, testimonies, evidence, notes taken by Weir during various hearing, and correspondence between the plaintiffs and their attorneys. These materials also contain a number of documents related to counter-suits filed against the B-men including one from their first attorney Sidney Gordon who sued to obtain unpaid legal fees in 1965, and another from PMA and ILWU leaders for libel. The collection also includes registration files and individual testimonies from the B-men involved in the case. Other materials include Stan Weir’s extensive research for the case, which contains a detailed index created by Weir.
The collection also contains administrative and editorial files from Weir’s publishing company Singlejack Books, which he started with Robert Miles in 1977. These materials consist of correspondence related to publications and the everyday operations of the company, manuscripts, financial records, and documents related to the dissolution of the firm in 1987.
There is also a small amount of correspondence between Weir’s mother Florence Hoggard Weir and his stepfather Albert Nicholas, who was one of founders of New Orleans jazz.
Historical/Biographical Note
Stan Weir (1921-2001) was an educator and labor activist from California. Born in Los Angeles in 1921, Weir had a long career in across a variety of industries, working as a seaman, autoworker, house painter, Teamster, grocery clerk, publisher, and university professor. As a young man Weir briefly attended Los Angeles City College for a term before he transferred to University of California-Los Angeles (UCLA). He later left UCLA to work as a cadet on a freighter along the Pacific Coast. Weir worked a number of jobs along the California coast, including a position as a merchant seaman where he became involved as a young union leader. As a union organizer Weir often found himself at odds with union bosses, and ultimately lost his job as a merchant seaman in 1945 for fighting against the Sailors Union of the Pacific’s policy of allowing segregation. In 1959 Weir began working as a longshoreman in San Francisco, where he was hired as a B class worker or “B-man” with the International Longshore and Warehouse Union (ILWU).
The ILWU had stopped admitting full-time members in 1948 and instead adopted a policy of bringing on new laborers under the B class registration status, a second-class industry classification. Workers hired as B-men paid full membership dues, but were not allowed full membership rights or protections as workers. In 1963 the union started a process of upgrading all B-men to an A registration status, however eighty-two workers who held B class registration status were fired and expelled from the union during this process. Weir was among the eighty-two longshoremen who lost their job in 1963. Weir and a number of other B-men filed a complaint in the US District Court in San Francisco, claiming that they had been expelled for political reasons rather than issues related to the quality of their work. For the next seventeen years, they fought to regain their right to work on the shorefront until the Supreme Court ultimately refused to hear their case.
Following his expulsion from the ILWU, Weir earned a Ph.D. at the Union Institute of Cincinnati and later worked as a professor of labor relations at the University of Illinois Champaign until he retired in 1980. Weir also founded the small press Singlejack Books with Robert Miles in 1977, which published labor related fiction and non-fiction. The company dissolved in 1987. Weir continued to write later into his life, and although he died in 2001, the University of Minnesota Press published his book Singlejack Solidarity in 2004.
Access Restrictions
The majority of this collection is open for research without restrictions. Registration files and attendance sheets in boxes 15 and 16 contain personally identifiable information and are restricted until 2037 or until individuals featured in these files are no longer living.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Stan Weir sent a gift of his papers in 1991. The accession number associated with this gift is 1991.016.
Labor and laboring classes.; Labor disputes -- United States.; Publishers and publishing; Stevedores -- Labor unions -- United States.; International Longshore and Warehouse Union; Pacific Maritime Association
- Union Registration Files and Plaintiff Interrogation Transcripts: Last Names L-M, 1957-1962 (Box 1, Folder 1-13, 21-23)
- Attendance Sheets and Employee Hours, 1957-1962 (Box 1, Folder 14-20)
- Union Registration Files and Plaintiff Interrogation Transcripts: Last Names C-L, 1962-1972 (Box 2, Folder 1-14)
- Pacific Maritime Association-International Longshoreman and Warehouse Union Lawsuit: Advocacy Work, Fundraising, and Notes Regarding the Suit, 1964-1968 (Box 3, Folder 1-56)
- Union Registration Files and Plaintiff Interrogation Transcripts: Last Names N-P, 1962-1974 (Box 4, Folder 1-10)
- Stan Weir: Time Off Inquiry and Deregistration, 1963-1965 (Box 4, Folder 11-12)
- Legal Briefs: Keylor vs. Pacific Maritime Association and Gordon vs. Pacific Maritime Association, 1963-1965 (Box 4, Folder 13-22)
- Pacific Maritime Association-International Longshoremen and Warehouse Union Lawsuit: Exhibits and Research, 1962-1974 (Box 5, Folder 1-8, 11-25)
- Pacific Maritime Association-International Longshoreman and Warehouse Union Lawsuit: Sidney Gordon Fired as Attorney, 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 9-10)
- Research on Waterfront Workers, 1935-1974 (Box 6, Folder 1-37)
- Singlejack Books: Typescripts, Paste-ups, and Manuscripts, 1978-1990 (Box 7, Folder 1-35)
- Singlejack Books: Non-Profit Status and Internal Revenue Service (IRS) Dispute, 1985-1990 (Box 8, Folder 1-34)
- Singlejack Books: Correspondence Regarding Publications, 1978-1987 (Box 8, Folder 35-56)
- Pacific Maritime Association-International Longshoreman and Warehouse Union Lawsuit: Local Bulletins, Harry Bridges Libel Suit, and Depositions, 1962-1980 (Box 9, Folder 1-30)
- Pacific Maritime Association-International Longshoreman and Warehouse Union: Union Organizing, Various Cities, 1958-1976 (Box 10, Folder 1-61)
- Stan Weir Note Cards: Notes on Arbitration Cases and Research, 1958-1976 (Box 11)
- Pacific Maritime Association-International Longshoreman and Warehouse Union Lawsuit: Press Coverage and Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 12, Folder 1-26)
- Pacific Maritime Association-International Longshoreman and Warehouse Union Lawsuit: Stockton B-Men, undated (Box 12, Folder 27-41)
- Singlejack Books: Gilbert Mers "Fight Against Shutdowns" Manuscript, 1982 (Box 13, Folder 1-10)
- Singlejack Books: Staughton Lynd "Fight Against Shutdowns" Manuscript, 1982 (Box 13, Folder 16-20)
- Florence Hoggard Weir and Albert Nicholas Correspondence, 1953-1954 (Box 13, Folder 11-15)
- California Unemployment Insurance Board Hearings, 1970s (Box 14, Folder 1-27)
- Registration Files and Attendance Sheets, 1957-1962 (Box 15, Folder 1-28, Box 16, Folder 1-3)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Access to Box 15 and 16 is restricted until 2037.